Guide to the Ralph Heyward Isham Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ralph Heyward Isham papers
1780-1976
MS 1455
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, business and financial documents, photographs, and printed material which document Ralph Heyward Isham's British army service and his collecting and publishing of the James Boswell Papers.
Isham, Ralph Heyward, 1890-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jonathan Isham in 1986; transfer from Boswell Papers, SML, in 1996 and 1997.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and two additions: I. British Intelligence Files, 1917-1949. II. Boswell Papers Files, 1921-1949.
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Heyward Isham Papers contain correspondence, topical files, business and financial documents, photographs and printed material which document Isham's British army service and his collecting and publishing of the James Boswell papers. The papers were donated to Manuscripts and Archives by Jonathan Isham in 1986. The three linear feet of papers are arranged in two series: I. BRITISH INTELLIGENCE FILES and II. BOSWELL PAPERS FILES.
Series I, BRITISH INTELLIGENCE FILES, consists of materials relating to Isham's work as head of a British army intelligence unit known as A-2, G.H.Q. When British soldiers were not demobilized immediately after the armistice in November of 1918, some disgruntled troops conducted "strikes" and refused to parade or obey orders. Isham's work in dealing with disaffection among troops at his command was brought to the attention of Field Marshall William Robertson who appointed Isham to his staff in 1918 to investigate and suppress Bolshevik activities which were believed to be responsible for the strikes. In order to assist him in accomplishing these goals, Robertson authorized the formation of the A-2 branch at General Headquarters. Isham was named director with a major and six other officers under his command. Through undercover investigations of suspected Bolsheviks and lectures to troops on the dangers of Bolshevism, the A-2 Branch was successful in ending and preventing strikes among servicemen. Subsequently, the A-2 Branch was placed within the Home Office so that Isham could conduct investigations and take disciplinary action against nonmilitary British citizens who were believed to be involved in traitorous activities.
Materials within the series include administrative correspondence and memoranda; correspondence between Isham and his agents; investigative reports by agents on individuals, organizations, and locations; records of the lecture program which describe the units addressed and impressions of troop morale; printed material; and several photographs.
Series II, BOSWELL PAPERS FILES, consists of correspondence, business and financial records, printed material and photographs related to Isham's collecting and publishing of the papers of James Boswell and Isham's involvement in the literary arena. Correspondents include the Talbots de Malahide from whom Isham obtained Boswell material; William Rudge, the printer of the eighteen-volume The Private Papers of James Boswell from Malahide Castle in the Collection of Lt.-Colonel Ralph Heyward Isham; Charles Getts, who, as Isham's agent arranged the collector's speaking engagements, and numerous individual and institutional subscribers to the Papers. The bulk of the business and financial records consists of invoices, receipts, inventories, sales accounts, and subscriber lists from William Rudge.
Biographical / Historical
Ralph Heyward Isham was born in New York City on July 2, 1890. He attended Cornell University (1908), Yale College (1910-1911), and New York Law School. He served in the British army during World War I, and following the armistice in November of 1918 he was named head of an intelligence unit which investigated and suppressed Bolshevik activities among militiary personnel. For his army service he was made a Commander of the Order of the British Empire, and retired at the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. Isham returned to New York City and was associated with a number of business concerns including Trumbull Securities Corporation, of which he was president. His avid collecting of James Boswell papers resulted in the private publication of The Private Papers of James Boswell from Malahide Castle in the Collection of Lt.-Colonel Ralph Heyward Isham (1928-1934) in eighteen volumes. He died in New York City in 1955.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Communism -- Great Britain; Intelligence service -- Great Britain; World War, 1914-1918 -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- History -- George V, 1910-1936; Boswell, James, 1740-1795; Isham, Ralph Heyward, 1890-1955
- British Intelligence Files, (1917-1920)-1949; Series I; 1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by name of individual, organization or topic. Files containing three photographs and the chronologically arranged printed material appear at the end of the series.
  - A2 Branch
    - Organization, 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Precis of papers received, 1919 April-September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beaudrie, John T., 1919 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Billet, 1919 January-November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bolshevism in England, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Byrnes, John C. [Agent No. 8]
    - Accounts, 1919 May-1920 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1919 May-1920-Jan, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Duplicate [supplementary] reports, 1919 May-Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and notes (miscellaneous), 1919 March-October (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gray, G. R.
    - Correspondence, 1919 March-Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Reports, 1919 March-Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Isham, Ralph H.
    - Lectures - private notes, 1918 December-1919 Mar, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Papers for France, 1919 April-July undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Private notes and memoranda, 1918 Feb, 1919 January-1920 January, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Lectures
    - Correspondence, 1919 March-Nov, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Reports, 1919 March-Oct, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lee, Melville, 1919 Apr, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Leeper, R. A., 1919 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Leland, F. W. G., 1919 May-October (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lucas, C. C., 1927-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Michod, P. D., 1919 Mar, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - N. S. L., [agent] (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Page Croft, H., 1919 June-July (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Parkes, Stanley, 1919 March-April (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Pearson, Arthur, 1919 April-1920 January (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pickering, C. J., 1919 July (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pridham, G. R., 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pym, H., 1919 July-October (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Reports by agents
    - Battersea and Kempton Park, 1919 February (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Conscientious objectors meetings, 1919 April (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Ewer, W. Norman, 1919 February (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Gallacher, William, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Ginnett, Mr., 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Liverpool, 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Paul, Willy, 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Petrograd, 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Ramsay, David, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Smillie, Robert, 1919 March (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Soldiers, Sailors and Airmen's Union, 1919 March-Jun, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Troy, Lillian Scott and Von Horst, Baron, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - West of Scotland Soviet Conference, 1919 March (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Woolwich Shop Stewards and the Communist Club, 1919 March-May (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919 March-Oct, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Robertson, William R., 1925-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Romer, Cecil, 1925-1942 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Saleeby, Dr., 1919 May (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Thompson, S., 1919 March-November (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Thomson, Basil, 1919 March-Nov, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Photographs
    - C. C. Lucas with others, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - M. S. Mundy, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Printed material, 1917-1919, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Boswell Papers Files, 1921-1949; Series II; 1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically within divisions by type of material.
  - Correspondence
    - Anderson Galleries, Inc., 1926, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Bodleian Library, 1929, 1932-1938 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Boswell, James, Lord Talbot de Malahide and Joyce Talbot de Malahide, 1927-1948 (Box 4, Folder 56-59)
    - British Museum, 1929-1934, 1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Brown, Joseph E., 1931-1935 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Bumpus, John & Edward, Ltd., 1926-1930 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Chadbourne, Hunt, Jaeckel & Brown, 1926-1929, 1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Crary, Mary, 1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Denton, Hall & Burgin, 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Doubleday, Mrs. Frank, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Ellis, Richard [The Georgian Press], 1929 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Getts, Clark H., 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
    - Hyde, Donald F., 1948, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Kennerley, Mitchell, 1929-1930, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - London Library, 1929-1932 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Miller, Frank, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - New York Public Library, 1930-1931, 1937, 1942, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Nichol Smith, D., 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Oxford University Press, 1937, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Pottle, Frederick A., 1929-1931, 1937, 1940, 1944-1945, 1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Princeton University, 1931, 1937-1938 undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Putnam and Company, Ltd., 1937 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Rice Institute, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Rivière, Robert and Son, 1923-1931 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Rogers, Bruce, 1928-1932, 1934, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Royal Bank of Ireland, 1928, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Rudge, William E., Publisher, 1929-1935 (Box 5, Folder 84-88)
    - Whibley, Leonard, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Yale University Library, 1927-1928, 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - A - G (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - H - L (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - M (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - N - R (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - S - Y (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Unidentified (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Business and financial records
    - Lists of manuscripts, 1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Miscellaneous documents and notes regarding publications, undated (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Miscellaneous receipts and statements, 1928-1949 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Rivière, Robert & Son, Ltd., 1921-1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Robertson, D. O., 1924 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Rudge, William E., Publisher
      - Inventories, 1934, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Invoices and receipts, 1929-1935 (Box 6, Folder 103-104)
      - Sales accounts, 1927-1934 (Box 6, Folder 105)
      - Statements of account, 1930-1935, undated (Box 6, Folder 106)
      - Subscribers lists, 1930-1935 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Photographs of James Boswell, Mary Crary, and unidentified pair of men, 1948, undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Printed material, 1930, 1937, undated (Box 6, Folder 109)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-024
  This addition to the Ralph Heyward Isham Papers consists of correspondence; business and financial records; and printed material pertaining to Isham's collecting and publishing of the papers of James Boswell.
  - Boswell Papers Files
    - Correspondence
      - Personal/family, 1920, 1925, 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - A-D (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Bank of Ireland [includes Edinburgh materials], 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Brandt and Brandt [includes legal agreements], 1930-1937, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Butterfield, L. H., 1948 January 8-October 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Chapman, R. W.
        - 1923-1930 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
        - 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Chase National Bank, 1946 August-1947 February (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Denton, Hall and Burgin
        - 1924-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      - Doubleday, Page & Co., 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - F-H (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Gauss, Christian and Alice, 1930-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Harvard University [includes request to obtain Isham's Boswell collection], 1929, 1939, 1948, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Hilles, Frederick W. [includes typescripts of Sir Joshua Reynolds], 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Hyde, Donald and Mary, 1949-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - I-P (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Lewis, Wilmarth, 1930-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Liebert, Herman, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - McGraw Hill Publishing Co., 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - McKenzie, Hyde, Murphy and Law [includes legal agreements], 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Morshead, Owen, 1937-1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - New York Public Library, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Oxford University Press/Clarendon Press, 1939, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Pottle, Frederick A. [correspondence primarily with Isham; also includes numerous publishers]
        - 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 27-32)
        - 1935 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - 1937-1943, 1953-1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Additional correspondence [includes letters pertaining to manuscripts from Fettercairn House]
          - 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 35)
          - 1938-1945 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
          - 1947 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        - Scott, Geoffrey [to and from Pottle], 1928 July-1929 February (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Q-T (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Rogers, Bruce (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Salpeter, Harry
        General
        See: box 2, folder 43
      - Scott, Geoffrey
        - [correspondence to/from Isham and others; includes letters of condolence re Scott's death], 1924, 1928-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
        - [includes papers re Scott's estate], 1928-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Simon and Schuster, 1937-1943 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Spingarn, Arthur B., 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Talbot family [of Malahide]
        - 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
        - Inventory of letters from Boswell estate, 1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1926-1937 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - U-Z (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Van Alen, James H., 1927-1937, 1942, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Viking Press/Guinzburg
        - 1930-1937 (Box 2, Folder 52)
        - 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - William Edwin Rudge, Inc. [includes legal agreements]
        - 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 54)
        - 1935-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - William Heinemann Ltd., 1930, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Yale Library Associates, 1940, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Yale University Library, 1940-1954 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Unidentified, 1929, 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Subject Files
      - Bank statements, 1928, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Books, cost of, 1927, 1929, 1940-1948 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence [inventory of incoming/outgoing] (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Estate legal documents
        - 1937 January-May (Box 3, Folder 63-64)
        - 1939 January-October-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 65-69)
      - Expense records, 1927-1939, 1946-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Manuscripts [cost of acquisition/related expenses], 1927-1947 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Manuscripts/books [inventory], 1934, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Notes [miscellaneous], undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Notes [re the manuscripts], 1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Printed material, 1911, 1928-1934, 1946, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Project costs, 1932, 1946-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Yale Library Associates, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 77)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-098
  This addition to the Ralph Heyward Isham Papers consists of correspondence, inventories, and background information relating to the acquisition of the Boswell Papers.
  - Boswell Papers Files
    - 1780-1798 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - 1800-1806 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1812-1828 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1833, 1835, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1873, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1905, 1917, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - June (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - July-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - January-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - July-December (Box 1, Folder 12)